<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE xsl:stylesheet [
  <!ENTITY nl "&#10;">
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY sq "&#x25A1;">
  ]>

<doc name="Getting Started" 
     type="GettingStarted"
     briefdescription="Introductory notes and installation instructions">
    <para>
        This chapter gives an overview of this package, including its purpose,
how to install it and any known issues at the time of release.
    </para>


<!-- ****************************************************************** -->

  <section name="What is the GUI Layout Toolbox?" staticref="about">
    <keywords>About</keywords>
<P>
The GUI Layout Toolbox provides a package of MATLAB objects that allow for complex
arrangement of graphical user interface elements within a figure window. The
main capabilities provided are:
<UL>
  <LI>Automatic element arrangement horizontally, vertically or in grids</LI>
  <LI>Ability to specify fixed sizes or resizing weights for each element</LI>
  <LI>Ability to "nest" layouts to produce virtually any element arrangement</LI>
  <LI>Divider bars for user-resizing of elements</LI>
</UL>
</P>
<P>
These element arrangement capabilities are designed to match those found as
standard in other user-interface toolkits such as Java Swing, GTK, QT etc.
</P>
    <P>
        Note that this is the second version of this toolbox, designed to 
        work with MATLAB releases R2014b and later. For earlier MATLAB releases
        use the first version.
    </P>
</section>


<!-- ****************************************************************** -->

<section name="Release Notes" staticref="releasenotes">
    <para>
        The GUI Layout Toolbox version numbers take the form <code>major.minor.iter</code>. The
        current version you have installed can be checked by typing <matlabfcn>ver</matlabfcn>
        at the MATLAB command prompt.
    </para>
    
    
    <inlinesubsection name="Version 2.0.5">
        Minor changes (14 May 2014)
        <ul>
            <li>Updated default styles and colours for BoxPanel for a different, more modern, look</li>
        </ul>
    </inlinesubsection> 
    
    <inlinesubsection name="Version 2.0.5">
        Minor changes (7 February 2014)
        <ul>
            <li>Added documentation</li>
        </ul>
    </inlinesubsection> 
    
    <inlinesubsection name="Version 2.0.3">
        Minor changes (27 November 2013)
        <ul>
            <li>Improved appearance of flexible dividers</li>
            <li>Modified default tab titles to match GLT1 behavior</li>
            <li>Modified button resize behavior to shrink-to-fit in button boxes</li>
            <li>Modified default button box horizontal alignment to 'center'</li>
            <li>Added support for row values for property 'Contents'</li>
            <li>Fixed bugs in uiextras.Grid accessors for property 'Heights'</li>
        </ul>
    </inlinesubsection> 
    
    <inlinesubsection name="Version 2.0.2">
        Minor changes (19 November 2013)
        <ul>
            <li>Added support for row values for contents companion properties in uix</li>
            <li>Modified uix.Image to construct JLabel on EDT</li>
            <li>Added HandleVisibility awareness to uix.ChildObserver</li>
            <li>Suppressed constructor warnings in uiextras</li>
        </ul>
    </inlinesubsection> 
    
    <inlinesubsection name="Version 2.0.1">
        Initial beta version (16 November 2013)
    </inlinesubsection> 
    
</section>


<!-- ****************************************************************** -->
  
<section name="Installation"> 
    <keywords>Uninstall</keywords>
    <para>
        To use this toolbox it must be added to the MATLAB path. Scripts are provided
        to do this in two ways:
    </para>
    <para>
        <b>From MATLAB:</b>
        <OL>
            <LI><b>From MATLAB:</b> from the folder containing the toolbox, run the "install.m" function</LI>
            <LI><b>From Windows Explorer:</b> from the folder containing the toolbox, double-click the "install.bat" icon</LI>
        </OL>
    </para>
    <para>
        To uninstall (i.e. remove it from the path), run the function 'uninstall' in MATLAB, also found in the toolbox folder.
    </para>
</section>

<!-- ****************************************************************** -->
  
<section name="Support"> 
    <keywords>Help</keywords>
    <p>
        This toolbox is not a MathWorks supported product. However, if you
        have problems, suggestions or other comments, please contact the
        authors:
    </p>
    <ul>
        <li><a href="mailto:david.sampson@mathworks.co.uk">David Sampson</a></li>
        <li><a href="mailto:ben.tordoff@mathworks.co.uk">Ben Tordoff</a></li>
    </ul>
    <p>If you like this toolbox, help others to find it by leaving a rating
        and comment on the <a href="http://www.mathworks.com/matlabcentral/fileexchange/?????">MATLAB Central File Exchange</a>.
    </p>
</section>

<!-- ****************************************************************** -->
  
<section name="Acknowledgements"> 
    <p>
        This toolbox has been evolving for several years and is based on the work of many engineering consultants
        at MathWorks, including (but not limited to):
    </p>
    <ul>
        <li>Ben Tordoff</li>
        <li>David Sampson</li>
        <li>Paul Kerr-Delworth</li>
        <li>Malcolm Wood</li>
        <li>Brad Phelan</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Many thanks to those who have shared their code and expertise over the years.</p>
</section>
<!-- ****************************************************************** -->
  
</doc>
