<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE xsl:stylesheet [
  <!ENTITY nl "&#10;">
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY sq "&#x25A1;">
  ]>

<doc name="Getting Started" 
     type="GettingStarted"
     briefdescription="Introductory notes and installation instructions">
    <para>
        This chapter gives an overview of this package, including its purpose,
how to install it and any known issues at the time of release.
    </para>


<!-- ****************************************************************** -->

  <section name="What is the GUI Layout Toolbox?" staticref="about">
    <keywords>About</keywords>
<P>
The GUI Layout Toolbox provides a package of MATLAB objects that allow for complex
arrangement of graphical user interface elements within a figure window. The
main capabilities provided are:
<UL>
  <LI>Automatic element arrangement horizontally, vertically or in grids</LI>
  <LI>Ability to specify fixed sizes or resizing weights for each element</LI>
  <LI>Ability to "nest" layouts to produce virtually any element arrangement</LI>
  <LI>Divider bars for user-resizing of elements</LI>
</UL>
</P>
<P>
These element arrangement capabilities are designed to match those found as
standard in other user-interface toolkits such as Java Swing, GTK, QT etc.
</P>
    <P>
        Note that this is the second version of this toolbox, designed to 
        work with MATLAB releases R2014b and later. For earlier MATLAB releases
        use the first version.
    </P>
</section>


<!-- ****************************************************************** -->

<section name="Compatibility considerations" staticref="compatibility">
    <inlinesubsection name="Minimum MATLAB version">
        <p>This is the second version of the GUI Layout Toolbox, designed to 
            work with MATLAB releases R2014b and later. For earlier MATLAB releases
        use the first version.</p>
    </inlinesubsection> 
    
    <inlinesubsection name="Compatibility with v1.x">
        <p>If you are upgrading from the first version of GUI Layout Toolbox,
    there are a number of compatibility considerations:</p>
    
<h4>Package name</h4>
<p>GLT1 packages were contained in the package 'uiextras'.  GLT2 classes are 
contained in the package 'uix'.  In GLT2, a package 'uiextras' is included 
to provide support for legacy code.  Classes in 'uiextras' extend 
corresponding classes in 'uix', and contain only compatibility-related 
code.</p>

<h4>Contents property</h4>
<p>The contents of GLT1 objects were accessible via the property 'Children'.  
The contents of GLT2 objects are accessible via the property 'Contents'.  
GLT2 objects also provide a property 'Children', but this controls the 
vertical stacking order of contents, rather than the layout order.  Legacy 
code that accesses 'Children' will run without error, but will not achieve 
the desired change in layout order, and should be modified to access 
'Contents' instead.</p>

<p>An upcoming release of GLT1 will include support for code that references 
contents via 'Contents'.  That way, code modified to work in GLT2 will also 
work in GLT1.</p>

<p>The background to this change is as follows.  GLT1 objects were wrappers 
for built-in graphics objects, and presented contents in layout order via 
the property 'Children'.  GLT2 objects extend built-in graphics objects, 
and as such, inherit properties, methods and events.  One such property is 
'Children' which is used to control the top-to-bottom stacking order.  
MATLAB stacking rules, e.g., controls are always on top of axes, mean that 
some reasonable layout orders may be invalid stacking orders, so a new 
property for layout order is required.</p>

<h4>Auto-parenting</h4>
<p>HG2 introduces unparented objects, i.e., those with property 'Parent' 
empty.  HG2 also introduces a separation between class constructors, e.g., 
matlab.ui.container.Panel, and construction functions, e.g., uipanel.  
These behaviors are related in that construction functions are auto-
parenting, i.e., if 'Parent' is not specified then it is set to gcf, 
whereas class constructors return objects with 'Parent' empty by default.  
GLT2 has adopted the HG2 pattern, with an HG2-like naming convention, e.g., 
class constructor uix.Grid and construction function uixgrid.</p>

<p>Classes in 'uiextras' are auto-parenting so the behavior of legacy code is 
unchanged.  However, best practice is to specify parent explicitly during 
construction.</p>

<h4>Defaults mechanism</h4>
<p>GLT1 provided a defaults mechanism -- 'get'/'set'/'unset' in 'uiextras' -- 
that mimicked HG1 'get' and 'set'.  This feature has been removed from 
GLT2.  Users should use an alternative programming pattern, e.g. factory 
function, to create objects with standard settings.</p>

<h4>Enable and disable</h4>
<p>GLT1 provided a mechanism to enable and disable container contents using 
the property 'Enable'.  This feature has been removed from GLT2.  Users 
should enable and disable controls directly rather than via containers.</p>

        <p>See related discussion at: <a href="http://goo.gl/j0KmTR">http://goo.gl/j0KmTR</a></p>

<h4>Other property name changes</h4>
<p>A number of property names have changed to achieve greater consistency 
across the package.  For example, 'RowSizes' and 'ColumnSizes' in 
uiextras.Grid are now 'Heights' and 'Widths' in uix.Grid.  The package 
'uiextras' provides support for legacy property names.</p>
<ul>
    <li><code>RowSizes</code> -> <code>Heights</code></li>
    <li><code>ColumnSizes</code> -> <code>Widths</code></li>
    <li><code>ShowMarkings</code> -> <code>DividerMarkings</code></li>
</ul>

<h4>Property shape changes</h4>
<p>GLT2 contents companion properties are now of the same size as 'Contents', 
i.e., column vectors.  In GLT1, these properties were row vectors.  The 
package 'uiextras' provides support for legacy property values.</p>

    <h4>Tab selection behavior</h4>
        <p>In GLT1, after adding a tab to a tab panel, the new tab is selected.</p>
        <p>In GLT2, the original selection is preserved, except if the tab panel was 
            empty, in which case the new tab is selected.  This is consistent with the 
        behavior of matlab.ui.container.TabGroup.</p>

    </inlinesubsection> 
    
</section>

<!-- ****************************************************************** -->

<section name="Release Notes" staticref="releasenotes">
    <para>
        The GUI Layout Toolbox version numbers take the form <code>major.minor.iter</code>. The
        current version you have installed can be checked by typing <matlabfcn>ver</matlabfcn>
        at the MATLAB command prompt.
    </para>
    
    
    <inlinesubsection name="Version 2.1">
        Released 28 August 2014
        <ul>
            <li>First release for R2014b</li>
        </ul>
    </inlinesubsection> 
    
    <inlinesubsection name="Version 2.0.7">
        Released 19 August 2014
        <ul>
            <li>Packaged as a MATLAB Toolbox (.mltbx)</li>
        </ul>
    </inlinesubsection> 
    
    <inlinesubsection name="Version 2.0.6">
        Released 13 August 2014
        <ul>
            <li>Added missing uix.Empty</li>
            <li>Removed internal class uix.EventSource</li>
        </ul>
    </inlinesubsection> 
    
    <inlinesubsection name="Version 2.0.5">
        Released 3 June 2014
        <ul>
            <li>Updated class and event names</li>
            <li>Updated default styles and colours for BoxPanel for a different, more modern, look</li>
        </ul>
    </inlinesubsection> 
    
    <inlinesubsection name="Version 2.0.4">
        Released 7 February 2014
        <ul>
            <li>Added documentation</li>
        </ul>
    </inlinesubsection> 
    
    <inlinesubsection name="Version 2.0.3">
        Released 27 November 2013
        <ul>
            <li>Improved appearance of flexible dividers</li>
            <li>Modified default tab titles to match GLT1 behavior</li>
            <li>Modified button resize behavior to shrink-to-fit in button boxes</li>
            <li>Modified default button box horizontal alignment to 'center'</li>
            <li>Added support for row values for property 'Contents'</li>
            <li>Fixed bugs in uiextras.Grid accessors for property 'Heights'</li>
        </ul>
    </inlinesubsection> 
    
    <inlinesubsection name="Version 2.0.2">
        Released 19 November 2013
        <ul>
            <li>Added support for row values for contents companion properties in uix</li>
            <li>Modified uix.Image to construct JLabel on EDT</li>
            <li>Added HandleVisibility awareness to uix.ChildObserver</li>
            <li>Suppressed constructor warnings in uiextras</li>
        </ul>
    </inlinesubsection> 
    
    <inlinesubsection name="Version 2.0.1">
        Released 16 November 2013
        <ul>
            <li>Initial beta version</li>
        </ul>
    </inlinesubsection> 
    
</section>


<!-- ****************************************************************** -->
  
<section name="Installation"> 
    <keywords>Uninstall</keywords>
    <para>
        GUI Layout Toolbox is packaged as a MATLAB Toolbox File (.mltbx).
    </para>
    <para>
        To install, open the file from within MATLAB or from the system file browser.
    </para>
    <para>
        To uninstall, go to to Add-Ons > Manage Custom Toolboxes within MATLAB.
    </para>
</section>

<!-- ****************************************************************** -->
  
<section name="Support"> 
    <keywords>Help</keywords>
    <p>
        This toolbox is not a MathWorks supported product. However, if you
        have problems, suggestions or other comments, please contact the
        authors:
    </p>
    <ul>
        <li><a href="mailto:david.sampson@mathworks.co.uk">David Sampson</a></li>
        <li><a href="mailto:ben.tordoff@mathworks.co.uk">Ben Tordoff</a></li>
    </ul>
    <p>If you like this toolbox, help others to find it by leaving a rating
        and comment on the <a href="http://www.mathworks.com/matlabcentral/fileexchange/27758-gui-layout-toolbox">MATLAB Central File Exchange</a>.
    </p>
</section>

<!-- ****************************************************************** -->
  
<section name="Acknowledgements"> 
    <p>
        This toolbox has been evolving for several years and is based on the work of many engineering consultants
        at MathWorks, including (but not limited to):
    </p>
    <ul>
        <li>Ben Tordoff</li>
        <li>David Sampson</li>
        <li>Paul Kerr-Delworth</li>
        <li>Malcolm Wood</li>
        <li>Brad Phelan</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Many thanks to those who have shared their code and expertise over the years.</p>
</section>
<!-- ****************************************************************** -->
  
</doc>
